Now, we'll call it over the regular meeting for the Minor City Council for August 15th, 2022.
Any public input on scheduled personal appearances?
Three interlocal agreement between the City of Miami, Oklahoma,
Miami, Oklahoma, and Northeastern Oklahoma, and A&M College in support of the local small business development center.
A couple of weeks ago, we had Sandra Peer come and talk to you about what they are doing with the small business.
A business development center at NEO.
That was sort of done as a preliminary to this.
There's an agreement between the City and NEO that we would help support financially that development center.
And this is formalizing that agreement.
It is to cover two fiscal years.
And that, I'll answer any questions you might have.
It is located at NEO and they're basically serving as the fiscal agent for them.
This is a state project or state program.
But it has to be facilitated through some place.
And so NEO is doing that.
There are other partners that are helping with the financial support of doing this.
Our commitment to them was that it would be $10,000 per fiscal year.
Is this outside the one that we have down town already?
Is that a different one?
This is the entrepreneurial thing that's, so this is totally separate.
Okay, so the thing that the chamber or maids started a while back a couple years ago?
Yeah, I'm sorry, but I'm less familiar with that when it was started before my time.
But I know a little bit about what you talked about.
So then how is this one different than that one do you know?
I don't know that I could explain the differences, but I could probably explain more about this particular one.
Shannon here.
Shannon's here.
I'll try it.
So down town, what you have when we call that small business center.
That's essentially we provide an...
opportunity for businesses, especially small groups that just need office space, they need to
place to be able to set up, have a desk, have access to phone, internet, things of that
nature.
So it's more of an incubator to help them get started until they can finally grow to the
point where they can go off on their own.
So that's kind of what we're doing with the Chamber of Mades Office.
Right now we have the Biome news records there, SMX, which is an employment agency, essentially
for Red Collar, and then we have Mike Woodruff, who does his business through there as well.
He works the radio station and has his own business.
What Sandra does is specifically work with small businesses to help them get established
as far as she will help them in the development of business plans.
She will help them with access to workforce development issues.
That's primarily her area of expertise.
And that's where she focuses.
Also case and point, we have a business that reached out to us as looking for a location right
now in my Emma.
And one of the things we're working to be working on with him with Sandra and her office is developing
a business plan so that he can go out and begin the process of securing funding for that business.
For me, with the way Mades works, Mades is not a, you go to us first.
You go to the local lending institutions and you apply for financial help there.
You're trying to get your loan through the regular banks that are available here.
If in fact, you go through that process and the banks, because it's a new business, it's a new
venture.
There's not a lot of history to be able to approve a loan on.
And you can come to Mades and we offer a little bit more of, and I hate to use the term,
but higher risk financing.
So we're at a little higher interest rate than the lending institutions are, but there's a process
there.
Sandra's role is to help get you ready for that.
And so it is a big service to the community, but it's also a big service on a workforce development
standpoint.
And that she can help you with not only training you on how to effectively run your business.
She can help you and dealing with any workforce issues and help you with all of the startup
paperwork that you need in order to be successful and going out and obtaining that funding.
So this particular program is something that Dr. Stafford was very familiar with from his time
in Durant.
And whenever he came here and we started talking about this and we had reached out to the homeless
small business development, that was the value of this is with a few partners going together
and each sharing in the initial cost and the state picks up the rest of the cost and provides all
of the training and everything else plus we get access to her entire network, which they have
these people all over the state.
So if she's got a...
particular business in mind that maybe she doesn't have as much experience with, she can reach out to her network and find someone with specific skill sets to be able to help them.
But that's the idea is that by having this locally it's a free resource available to our community to help small businesses get off the ground and do it more safely and have a better success rate.
Thank you.
Four contingent staff are commensally approved out of five and six.
Hi.
Seven.
Mayor's nomination of Brad Williams to complete the council member term for award four.
Eight.
The measure of the oath of office to Mr. Brad Williams.
First, I have to use the board for.
Please.
Do solemnly swear or pardon.
I'm sorry.
That I'm a support of a independent constitution of the United States.
And the constitution of the state of Oklahoma.
And then I will not knowing we received directly or indirectly.
The performance or loan performance at any act of duty pertaining to my office.
Other than the compensation amount by law.
I further swear or pardon.
That I will pay fully discharge.
According to the best of our ability.
The duties of my office.
There is such time as I remember.
As the United City Council for court.
And the Board of Trustees.
As the United especially until the authority.
of the city of May of the moment.
All right, number nine.
Mayor's nomination of Brian Eastett to serve as Mayor Prodium.
Motion.
Second.
Williams.
Ten.
Mayor's nomination to appoint Brad Williams to serve as exficio on the Mama
Downtown Redevelopment Authority.
11.
Budget amendment.
22-35.
The General Fund worked comp.
Hemen Resources.
Mr. Michael.
Thank you, Mayor.
What this is, this is the last budget amendment for FY2122.
Just allowing us to move funds from the expense of the General Fund to an expense
of the county and the work comp fund to cover the audit or the work comp excess coverage.
All the funds are available.
Again, it's just to close out the final FI2122.
Thank you.
Second.
So full time.
Eastern Williams.
Seven.
Five.
Twelve.
General Fund.
Budget amendment.
No.
23-03.
Capital Improvement Projects.
För Fire Police.
Moving CIP funds.
For Union Contract raise.
Yes, sir, this is the FY2223.
The Police and Fire Contracts are negotiated after the budget is made.
is made, this year we have to move some funds to cover those raises that are endotored by
the contract. They are coming from the CIP fund, $66,000 coming off of a project that was planned
for the Coleman.
We'll be moved to the general fund to pay the salaries for police and fire.
What project was it?
So what in any specific project other than we had an engineering study that was going to be done,
that was budgeted roughly at 100,000 plus any potential repairs.
But after talking with Kevin, the determined that likely just the evaluation will take the majority of this fiscal year
that we won't likely have any repairs that will come up this fiscal year.
So we deemed that that money would be available from 100,000.
It was there knowing that if anything comes up significant,
that needs to be repaired at the coalmen.
We're going to have to take a good hard look at that since some of those items
could be deemed life safety issues like the firescape and things that we know need to be worked on.
But those will be in next fiscal year.
More than likely.
There's another question for Mike, your mobile on that.
Second.
Hi.
Senator.
Does that work?
Looks fine.
Thank you.
13.
Under authority of Ornith's 2022-07.
The City Council will consider adoption of Ornith's 2022-11.
To close that certain planet alley located in the block two of the we edition
to the city of Miami, Oklahoma City Council would determine whether there are any holders or
franchise or others who have special right or privileges to the alley to use the alley.
I'm not sure if he's going to go first.
Kim, give me a first.
We have.
We have some.
At least.
Maybe two people that are wanting to speak on this issue.
Do you.
Do you want to go first?
Okay.
I'm here.
Really.
Yes.
Okay.
Are you.
Pretty good.
Good evening.
Council member.
My name is John Graham.
The Vice President of Senior Legal Council for AT&T.
I'm here tonight because my clients and I receive a letter requesting our presence
to see if he to.
Lay claim to any property rights or the use of the alley way that's a question here.
I spoke to you, City Attorney, and your City Manager a couple of days ago.
And I'm here to express what I believe is our legal right to have our facilities within the right way that alley.
Specifically, I'm referring to Article 9, Section 2 of Oklahoma Constitution.
If you like, I have a copy of it.
If you would like to read along with me or.
I'd like to read it while you're sitting there.
Matt approach.
I don't know if you can hear him out.
Yeah.
The normal rules don't apply because this is relating
specifically to the agenda.
Okay, I'm pleased with that.
Yes.
Thank you.
Sure.
As you can see from the wording of this,
Article 9, Section 2 of Oklahoma Constitution,
gives among other entities including AT&T,
and your other public utility companies,
the right to be in the right ways in the state of Oklahoma.
As part of this, I did the research back to 1821,
part of statehood.
AT&T's original rights were provided to us by the federal government
by the Department of Interior, which gave us the right to be
in the right ways throughout the state of Oklahoma.
And the right way that you're making reference to our discussing this evening
is one we believe we have the right to be in the right way.
We believe the Constitution gives us the right along with the federal government.
And if you have any questions,
we'll want to answer any questions you may have.
So while AT&T has no objection to the closures you're recommending,
but our own objection would be if you take some action that would
affect our right to be in the right way.
So we're wanting to relocate that right away.
And the other utilities are okay with relocating to the new right away.
That'll be available.
Is AT&T not okay?
AT&T is a meaningful to moving the right way, however, but not at our expense.
I spoke to Mr. Risa, Mr. Lorraine of this past Wednesday.
And I actually know that they actually will be willing to sit down and talk with the city council
and the groups and I said yes, we will go down.
We want to sit down and talk with them to see if we can reach some compromise.
However, I'll be candid with you.
The compromise cannot start nor end with AT&T paying the cost to move.
So we're willing to work with the duo to see what we can, but if we rerout it,
we don't believe we should absorb the cost of moving those facilities.
Do we know what the cost would be from AT&T?
I'm sorry. I don't have the exact cost.
No, this is not the first time this issue has come up.
I think the past has been some discussion.
But what the cost would be today.
I couldn't tell you, you know, if the cost is going up on everything,
here in the last year or so, I couldn't have given you a ballpark idea
like to what the cost may be.
So this would be something that AT&T would be willing to partner with the city on.
This is a big economic development opportunity for the city.
We'd help us grow.
And that growth would actually help AT&T in the long run as well.
So is this something that we could partner on?
The expenses on?
Well, I say I'm not in a position to say exactly what AT&T may or may not do as far as that concern.
But I'm here to tell you that we're willing to sound and negotiate to see what we can come up with.
You know, if you look back at the history, you know, AT&T has been a good corporate citizen, I believe,
and we've always been and we've never had any problems.
We don't believe this is something that could cause us probably day.
I think we sit out and work out something.
We can come up with some type of resolution.
Well, that's why I'd here.
That's what exactly that's what we want to do as well.
That's trying to come to agreement that we can all be happy with.
We'll help us move forward with the economic development.
That's key piece.
Try to build our community that we, you know, we need to do something with.
And the, the, what's wanting to go there wants to go right in the middle.
And I don't believe AT&T would allow to be built over on top of, right?
Correct.
So, and the, the new businesses want to be in the middle.
I think they're required to, by the specifications of how the new buildings will be built,
would have to be located in the middle.
So, it would be brought one of the, the duck around is.
You know, in part of our discussion, you know, because there's what this federal funds out there
that might be able to assist in moving, you know, to got the ARPA funds that are sitting out there that you could use for economic development.
That you know, you might look to that as far as helping with defray the cost as well.
But, like I said, you know, we're here because, you know, we receive a letter access to to be here present tonight.
The question I'd be, is there anything further to be present tonight?
Because this is just a meeting here.
Okay.
So, what about the issue of franchising rights?
If I'm going to run.
We do not, AT&T and other are like local exchange companies operating state have a franchise agreement with the city.
Years ago, a agreement was placed and was put together by the cities and the companies.
We pay the city a initial inspection fee in lieu of the entire franchise.
We pay 2% of the basic local exchange rates, which would be paid for years.
And as part of my presentation, I'm getting prepared for this.
I check to make sure we are up to date on our payment to the city of Miami.
We appreciate you coming.
Thank you.
We look forward to working with you on this.
We've been very successful throughout the state.
And I don't think this is going to be something that will slow us up or be an anomaly.
I agree.
Thank you.
Thank you, gentlemen.
The fourth day we know we did a deck action.
First, Mr. Prometley, are you wanting to speak?
I don't know Mr. Graysley.
Okay.
Thank you.
And there's nobody else here in the audience wanting to address this issue.
Well, Ed, it's your choice.
You always have the right to respond this to a later date.
There will be further discussion on it after that other discussion.
The ordinance itself simply closes the street to the public,
which, as I understood, what Mr. Graysley said, they have no objection to doing that.
Yeah.
You like to resolve that?
No.
We have no objection to the alley bin closed.
However, we would object to any action taken that way for closed.
Our rights to be in the right way.
No.
Our very facilities.
And we have areas well.
And this is ordinance does not do that.
It closes the alleyway to the public.
Two.
We probably need to go ahead and do that.
You know what?
I think we need to table it until we have this further investigation
and conversations around what is the future look like, right?
Before we go putting an ordinance and we want to make sure that everything that we do is going to align for this to be successful.
My opinion.
You're right.
because if we close it, then we'd have to change it out like that.
So, we'll table 14, you need a motion for that, or just table.
It's clear, it's clear, it's clear.
I'm not a good motion, we'd table it.
It's not important.
14 or 13, sorry.
You're seconded?
Yes, I'm here.
You said five.
Seven, Bert?
Five.
Williams?
Hi.
Parker.
14.
I did the same thing.
We'll need to make a motion to table it.
That automatically gets table.
Okay.
You have to ask the motion.
15.
That's your tech contract, C18-47, extension of the 2023, 2022, and 23 in the mountain of
$50,000.
So, this is the same contract that you'll approve of.
See you next week.
Most of your approval.
Five.
Four.
Six.
16.
Outside organizational contracts for fiscal year 2223 with the Community Crisis Center and Grand Gateway
Pelavan.
So, for some historical background for Councilmember Williams, we have organizations and we use the same
template contract.
We call that group of organizations organizational contracts.
Normally we have three.
Right now I'm asking for two to be approved.
That would be the Grand Gateway Pelavan and the Community Crisis Center.
I'm not asking for the Senior Center at this time because they submitted a revised application
in the end of July, July 28.
So, we'll come back to you for that third organization.
Right now Pelavan is asking for the same amount that they've had since FY 1516.
And Community Crisis is asking for the same amount, which is a utility credit.
And they've had that same amount since FY 1213.
So, I'm asking for those two contracts to be approved.
How much are those utility credits?
Excuse me?
10,000.
Was that covered in their office on a street and the shelter?
I don't know their usage.
I would have to look back at the uses.
I'm sure it doesn't cover all of it.
They've submitted the same application every year.
I was actually kind of surprised.
In the Pelavan's 46,000?
Yes.
It would be in their application. I don't have their application with me.
I don't have a lot of the tribes.
The tribes would be one, I think.
Yes. Oh, yeah.
A lot of tribes also significant.
It's actually in your packet.
Application.
Yeah.
I'll stay funding.
Yes.
The Department of Transportation funding.
Oh, yeah.
And then I know last year we had significant questions about this contract.
And they did come and give a pre elaborate presentation.
That was very helpful.
So what we are proving the contracts for utility credits or the contracts as a whole.
It's two separate contracts.
One with Pelavand.
Right. Right.
Because we listed them separately on the same agenda item.
That's what we've been doing for the last few years.
So the crisis center is specifically request credit.
And I think the Pelavand is specifically a payment.
It's a reimbursement.
Yes.
For their expenses.
After 46.
I thought you didn't say it.
I'll say it.
Hi.
Williams.
Don't go.
Hi.
17.
Master customer agreement.
And attached.
Adenda.
With motor level solutions.
Watch your heart system for the vehicle and body camera system.
Yes.
This is our body one camera and our car camera.
We're at a training and our car system.
Our current system is watch guard.
It's approximately 10 years old.
It's at reach end of life.
It is a server-based system.
So all that storage is local.
He is worked with several times on how to store all the videos.
On any call we go to.
There's really two or three officers.
That's two body camps, two car camps.
And that's every call or every traffic stop we have.
So there's a significant amount of video
accumulated there, absolutely critical for working nowadays.
We get a complaint on officer, first thing I say is,
hey, let me check the video and use like,
oh, you know what that big of deal.
I don't want to do it.
Let's just, you know, I just want to be a bear with it.
Most people just are dying at that point.
I see, yeah, everyone for officers was a video.
And also, most prosecutions that we get declined,
we don't have video the same.
So it is actually critical that we have the watch card system
or anybody who wants camera system, rather.
We've checked in the two different systems, the watch guard
and axon, which is made by Taser.
And there was about 200,000 difference
that's being the cheaper system or less expensive system.
It is a little different camera.
These are more user serviceable.
Our cameras now don't have replaceable batteries.
So in the batteries, they go on the charger.
The little body cameras go on the charger.
They eventually wear out.
We've set them off.
And we've done that numerous times.
These have an intranetable battery.
So you can change out the battery if it goes bad.
So they are more serviceable.
And it'll be a cloud-based system.
So it's not local storage, which is going to say IT.
And so a lot of money and storage and I'll keep that way.
It is.
Since it automatically downloaded the mobile back end of the station.
Actually, it's automatically downloaded from a car to a cloud-based.
Right now you have to pull into the station.
And it's either of our cars or the running suit.
We have receivers out there, download, and cameras.
It takes a while to download all the video and to do it down there.
Watch guard was recently purchased by Motorola.
It has taken us a minute to get this quote and get almost gave up on watch guard.
We actually buzzed this last year.
And through the transition to Motorola, it's taken us this long to get a reliable sales
when it'll do us talk to us and get our quotes updated.
I think we've actually worked on it now.
We've been pretty good response here lately in the last few minutes.
They just had a rough time through that transition period.
This quote is for 117,000.
It's broke down over five years.
This year, it'll be 35,944 in 10 cents.
And then 2349 after that for next five years.
You already got this year's budget.
Yes, it is budget.
It was in my capital agreement, budget this year.
My question.
David.
Hold on.
He's got Williams.
I have a marker.
Thank you.
18, Mayor's nomination to a point.
Toby Allen to the Model of CVB Board replacing Shannon Duhon.
It's about 30 to 30.
That's about 20.
Any new business that's a business that's supposed to be this agenda?
20.
Staff reports.
21.
Mayor or Council Community and Mathidence.
I want to talk about the County Fair a little bit.
If you guys didn't go, it was a good time.
Pretty much that was good.
The Buddy Show was really good.
I was out there with the Buddy Show.
For those special needs kids.
That was a cool deal.
To see those kids have to be a walk at animal and have fun.
That was a small and air to air.
That was six successful fair.
Got the rodeo coming up.
Not this weekend, but next weekend is the 26th of the 27th.
I believe.
And 12 time rodeo the year.
We want to see a rodeo.
I'm sure we'll be out there.
There's actually some cards up here if you need one about it.
But good events.
The I don't know if we talked about the heritage festival and our last meeting.
But another successful heritage festival as well.
So busy time for us in the events right now.
So if they're all doing well, I'll be pulled off well.
Bring a lot of visitors down.
And we'll get to you back for everybody on those.
Yeah, I just say.
Everybody for pulling out the heritage festival.
Man, he has a new group.
Did an amazing job.
Everybody pulled together.
It's really cool to sit back and watch it all.
And you'll be a part of it.
And even.
Even.
The.
Many.
Class for you.
I have.
I was.
I ran around with so many years ago.
Ten of the streets.
How many years?
Not as many as you.
I'm.
See.
I want to thank Amanda too.
She done an outstanding job this year.
As usual.
Her team is outstanding.
They're good people.
They know what they're done.
And it takes more than six months to even plan this ahead.
And get ahead of it.
So could those do you and your team?
Come on.
This year was easy.
Right.
You had a whole year to plan for last year.
Would you have a couple weeks?
And the barbecue.
Cook off.
I don't know how them judges do it.
Because they're went up bad piece of meat in the house.
Like day bone.
I ride around and when the gators and the sky gave us ribs.
And like a bunch of ribs.
And you know, both vegan and he.
who's not vegan that day, he was using those ribs,
and we were talking about how great these ribs were.
So we'll get there to the wards, that guy got 9th in ribs.
We were like, man, there's 8th better than this.
Because we were talking about how great they were,
and he got 9th.
So we missed out on some good ribs, it sounds like.
But all the guys at the barbecue cookoff
braved about it, Shannon, and Chuck, did not stand in job,
getting that put together and pulling that off.
So cut those to them on that, and those guys
are already talking about coming back next year.
So for the first time to have one, they said
we did really, really well.
So anybody else on that?
Brad, you don't have anything yet?
Well, I look forward to having something at some point.
But I do not today.
All right, 22, send your manager to the communications.
So may your members of the council, something I just
want to put on your radar, I'm not asking for you all to make
a decision today, but I want to make you aware of this,
my recommendation, and that is one of the contracts that Jill mentioned
that we normally put with these energy contracts,
the community crisis center, and the grand gateway,
is the senior center.
And as Jill had mentioned, they had requested an increase
in their contracts.
So it kind of automatically caused an additional scrutiny
on our part to understand why you're asking for additional funding
and so as we were looking into their application,
and meeting with folks to understand exactly the services they provide,
we did have some questions we wanted to answer.
So we ended up going out there and meeting with them at the facility.
And it was a great meeting, and I won't go into a great deal of detail
because we'll have hopefully another opportunity to talk about this.
But what I'd like to recommend, and it's something I mentioned to them,
is I think it's important given the situation that they're in
because most of these places, COVID,
had a very specific impact of very negative impact on these facilities
because they're relying on people to come out of their homes
and come down to a central community center.
And so COVID was obviously hard on their numbers,
and in hard on their revenues, and now they're trying to come out of that.
And they're very excited about pushing forward and growing their numbers.
And the long and the short of it is they need a partner in the city
to do that.
They need the city to be a partner with them.
And so my recommendation would be that, potentially,
our number of work study because they actually are a community center,
and they have access to public meetings and public services
and all kinds of public events that they can host out of that facility,
that we consider having our next work study at their facility.
It would give you all the numbers.
opportunity to meet them, and have them answer any of the questions you want to have.
But also give you all an opportunity at one time to the facility right there.
Since we have a core of being very easy.
So, I simply put that on your radar and I'm happy to talk with you all about the individually offline.
We think that might work out.
So, that was it.
Number 23, adjournment.
Motion.
Thank you.
All right.
Peace.